[Music]
uh tonight uh we're going to speak about
the idea of budha nature from other
schools and uh this subject got bigger
and bigger as I was working on I
finished it about five minutes ago and
uh I was mainly going to speak about one
special Tibet school's idea of BR nature
which is very prevalent in the world and
was very prevent in tobet for
about um 800 years uh
then I saw that there was a something on
the lower Indian schools idea of BU
nature like Abida schools and my only
school so I thought to throw in some of
that okay so we'll start there uh the
first is uh Abid school okay this is the
lowest of the four Great Schools of
ancient India uh by basika detail school
and I thought to tell you what they
think is good in nature okay and it each
of these gives you
like I wouldn't have done this probably
in the original 18 courses because a lot
of today's lecture is on wrong
ideas but um cuz people would remember
them and maybe they'd get a box out for
them uh but I think in the in-depth
courses we can start to go into
controversies and arguments uh between
different schools and when I was in the
monastery it was very rare for one of my
llamas to um pull out an actual book
from another school and let them speak
for themselves you know like in the
monastery textbooks it's always they
they think such and such and it's all
it's often presented as sort of
and uh it's not so bad when you read it
from the other textbooks VI so what I've
done is I've actually taken some other
schools textbooks and you'll be getting
a presentation from
them let's start with the Alida okay
they say they talk a lot about this kind
of Buddha nature
and there's a Sanskrit which you'll get
uh in early
October
[Music]
right say
Pap should translate
that yeah the Buddha nature of anay okay
the Buddha seed of an say of a person
who have seen this
and here's how they describe that
Buddha
say uh means uh I think you know this
expression I think we have it in one of
the other courses this is a very famous
expression in the aod d means PE wants
PE wants like don't need much CH sh
means happy with whatever you
get CH sh means is satisfied santosa
Right comes as one of the nas in N sura
okay
um and they pull this out of the Lotus
Sutra and
uh there are four kinds let me see one
is to be satisfied whatever clothing you
get like just Rags one is to be
satisfied with wherever you have to stay
or sleep
uh one is to be satisfied with whatever
people put in your bowl like whatever
you have to eat right and then the last
one is to be happy just sitting around
all day doing Dharma like p gawa means
happy to work on your mental afflictions
happy to study happy to do your
practices you know satisfied with those
four things happy to do
that so why would that be
RC L Nature
because those things to being yeah and
further you see so in fact in some cases
they might even describe an Arya as
being this kind of a person rather than
working on
emptiness perception or something like
that so anyway you get the idea that for
them a realization in the H schools very
Monkish denish is satisfied with a
little room in the corner and some rags
to wear and whatever to eat sit there
and do your practices all day that's
basically hinana ideal okay
so so they say uh the reason they call
Buddha nature or Buddha seed is that
this is the S if you don't have this you
can't get anywhere else that's just the
beginning you know then they say shim
means needless to say everything beyond
that but but you got to have this to
start with or you're never going to even
come to Diamond Mountain okay
all right by the way they also say that
the uhas the sutus accept this so this
is a Buddha nature according to the two
lower
schools now we get to mind only
presentation of Buddha
nature Sak means pure
undefiled s mean seed in the mind seed
in the
mind an undefiled mental
seed pure mental
seed and there's basically three steps
to developing a mental seed tum
sayum learning like what you're doing
right now uh contemplation what you
should be doing in the car and the way
home and then gum meditation which you
should be doing tomorrow after you get
your homework it says meditate 15
minutes on such and such I'm sure you're
all
okay uh that's those those three steps
to are necessary for all Buddhist devel
uh that learning then contemplation of
what you've learned and then meditation
on what You' contemplated even a body s
right that you have to do that
um if this
SE uh has not been developed through
those three processes but you have it
then that's the first kind of Buddha
nature right natural
rary natural Buddha nature innate Buddha
nature the one that everyone's born with
okay if this seed has not yet been acted
upon through those Buddhist uh processes
of learning uh contemplation meditation
then it's called
natural uh Buddha nature okay if the
same seed has been acted upon in that
way it's called devel vable budha nature
or developing okay so they also make
that distinction the lower two schools
don't make that distinction much but the
mind only school does make that
distinction that's a little bit
different from what we had right and
just to repeat what the MAA had
righta especially the natural good
nature was
what you have the Mind mostly your own
emptiness mainly of your mind yeah your
own emptiness mainly of your mind okay
and then the developable was things like
path of seeing or an in tantric way even
your five heaps like could turn into
right so see how it differs from the
mind only schools version it's important
for understanding what else we're going
to talk about tonight okay so get the
difference straight my only School
thinks there's some like little crystal
seed inside of
you and then uh if that's been acted
upon or whenever it's acted upon by
learning by the process we're going
through right now then that's going to
help you develop into a budha in so far
as it hasn't been acted upon or the part
that hasn't been acted upon the part
that's been with you all the time well
that's natural Buddha nature you see
it's kind of like a part which is being
acted upon and a part is not being acted
upon and it's sort of like a Crystal
Seed within it okay so the native
crystal seed that you've always had is
natural then the seed as it starts to
get acted upon or develop or cultivated
that it appears they believe that that
same
seed becomes a kind of developable in
nature okay but I don't think they would
say that you lose the first seed when
you start on the second seed okay like
somehow you stood up both of them right
and there's a lot of problems with this
idea and you'll see some debates in your
um in your in your reading I stuck in
some debates between majima and my only
about why this is not such a great idea
okay and talk talk about you can read
about it in about four or five weeks
okay I'm really ambitious with the
readings they're going to end up huge
and I thought I was reflecting that it's
probably even good that instead of
having this be your last entire tter
class and then you don't get one until a
week before you uh teach that you get up
you get the readings and then you'll
read them I'm sure in between and you
know digest them as they come out okay
that's my real idea
okay uh sorry remember what he said yeah
yeah yeah yeah yeah you can actually if
you're careful you can find everything
in the readings they'll be much they'll
be couched in much more formal language
debates and arguments and but you'll you
can Str them up uh which brings us to
[Music]
shent uh this is now oh first thing I
ever put up today was Bash anist
s the next thing I put up was mine only
now we're on to M right which is
everybody in Tibet says they're
M and
shentong uh write it down
first shentong is an idea about
emptiness that spread into bed from
about 1100 on okay its roots can be
traced back to about
1100 and um it became very popular the
practice of shenton
as as how to practice about emptiness
became a very prevalent in many schools
mainly in the kagu to some extent in the
nigma even in this even in some
sakas uh shentong became the way to
meditate on emptiness and then it was
attacked uh very seriously by jus Kaa
guil of J and everybody after them uh as
being very mistaken so today we're going
to cover shentong first I'm going to
cover shentong as if I was a shentong
okay and shentong means uh emptiness of
something else Shen means something else
Tong means empty okay it's not only a
view of emptiness it became a movement
you see so shentong is not only a name
for a kind of emptiness it's a name for
a way of thinking about emptiness and
and it became a movement and the
movement was strong for a while and then
died for a while and then came back and
then died again and like that you can
say there were three even um peaks of it
in Tibet say around
1300 and then around
uh 1750 and then around uh
1870s something like that okay there
were like Peaks where it was defended
very
strongly and so as I promised you're
going to get to hear from the textbooks
and most of the reading is from the
other textbooks of other schools I
wanted to tell you which textbooks okay
uh so that you know it's oranic and you
know
that the first one is called
say s means the Deep inner State dun
means State means inner s means deep or
profound deep inner
State and it's a book about really chck
channels drops it's it's a beautiful
road map of the inner body and we're
going to use it when we get to course 14
or whatever it is in the temp St and
there's a group of people working on it
already um it's a really really good
book on the inner
body uh and its author
is say
[Music]
karma uh Karma here has nothing to do
with Karma Sanskrit okay it's karma this
is Kapa this happens to be the third
Kapa okay this is the kapas are a great
uh one of the great traditions of the
kagu and um the fourth carapa for
example what's who's the most famous car
kagu weo kago
yeah
J okay okay just like Jesus the the Jew
right uh he was uh a kou just C was a
kou although he had a great s teacher
know also but um the fourth karmapa
actually is the one who gave Jessa his
first spouse back in East to bed so we
have a very strong connection with them
R means happens all on itself means self
produced when you see uh Buddhas that
you showed me one that come out of a
rock you know like you just see a Buddha
outline or or what profile in a rock or
a Tara comes out those are called rang
means just happened came out on its own
and d means Diamond it's an appropriate
name for someone who's into shendo which
you'll find out later because you could
read this as you know
self-produced uh wisdom of the diamond
you know so it's not a bad name for
someone teaching
chento we're going to be studying we're
going to be reading the readings you get
are actually from a
commentary by someone named jamun kto
who lived uh who died in 1899 for
example I'm going to write his name next
because he's the author of the second
text we're going to read which is
different from the commentary to this
text get it he wrote two books that
we're going to read the commentary to
this one and then his own book okay and
this part was translated by Winston H
and it's really nice it's a big section
in the text he's been working on it for
a
[Music]
while say shant
okay shentong means again that special
kind of emptiness which became the name
for the whole
school meaning what yeah view or world
view especially okay CH means uh book of
instruction TTI is a special genre of
Tibetan literature which is a book about
emptiness and there are lots of Tes just
means a book about
emptiness a book about emptiness
the version of emptiness called shent
which means emptiness of something else
something emptiness of other I call it
other emptiness in the
reading
sorry I call it uh other emptiness in
the reading although I don't like weird
words like that in
general okay da means Moon as you know
do means do diamond it means the diamond
Moon I translated it as the diamond Moon
the Moon is important in in to shentong
people because of the image of the
mistaking the image of a moon in the in
A Quiet Pond for being the moon itself
like if you go to alistar's house and
you go out behind and there's this Pond
swimming pool uh and uh on a quiet night
you might look down and see the moon and
you know for a second you you think
you're looking at the moon so it's this
idea of Illusion okay and the the
absence of that the non-existence of the
moon in the pond is emptiness you see
which is the diamond so it's appropriate
name that he gave his book The Moon of
diamond diamond moon or something
like I'm going to give you the author's
name say
J
um J culture was a very interesting
figure I mean to become so famous so
early right usually had to be dead for 4
500 years before you get famous in Tibet
or before they carve your books you know
but he was like some
extraordinary thinker he grew up in a
very troubled time in Tibet there was a
lot of fighting between different
religious factions um he got caught in
the middle of that in several
instances um he was one of the rare
Tibetans to become a real master of
letters in his time I mean he became a
great writer uh like out of 500 monks in
gon college and S Monastery in 1959
there were only two who could
write okay I mean but he was pretty
great writer um to me his style looks a
lot like jetas I think he must have
study Jetson cop scriptures a lot
because he takes jeton cop to task a lot
okay he has quite different views from
jeton cop but the way he presents things
and his language is very similar it's
like someone who really absorbed jet
Copa and wanted to emulate jet
CA
um and I think because of the trouble
that he had grown up in he started
movement called remman REM means uh
non-aligned movement and they they tried
to uh sort of bring the sex together by
uh drawing from different books like he
drew a lot from nma text and he drew a
lot from kagu text and so a lot of
the debate was going on between
different sects of kagu and that's a
long story but basically um the kagu are
split into four or five great lineages
like uh shagu kagu Jun kagu Dagu these
are all like different groups of kagis
and and a historian I once spoke to um
what's his name Matthew capin who's a
great nma kagu scholar said that he felt
it was because of the uh geographical
isolation of the different parts of
Eastern Tibet the kagu were big in
eastern Tibet and then there were huge
valleys like it took a lot of trouble to
go over the pass into the next Valley
and so these lineages sort of took on
their own characteristics and there are
a lot of differences between the
presentations after a few hundred years
and then there came to be some you know
friction and also just in general
between all the schools especially gupa
and countries um in certain periods of
Tibetan history there were some bad
times um so I think Jan K and someone
named neam uh who lived about the same
time they were very uh interested in
trying to heal this kind of division and
trying to bring together the different
philosophical ideas and trying to show
how maybe they weren't so so
unacceptably different after all and and
so he's known as the Great Master of the
reman movement which was you can think
of him as a synthesis between kagu and
nimba but mainly kagu okay um he's also
known as y gatov there's also a Dal Lama
name named y g so don't get confused and
gang I don't know if this is the g g or
G Monastery but um I think it might be
gwang would mean like Prince of gar and
I think gar is an area east of it
okay uh so we're going to study his
that's the author of the second book
we're going to study okay this book is
really cool I mean uh I asked Jean Smith
who's a follower of Shandong himself
okay this is one of the greatest
scholars in the west uh I asked him uh
give me the best book of shent because I
want to put it in the read you know so
he sent me Jung gun K's book and I
started to read it and it's very
beautiful because uh it's not very long
it's like 25 Pages or something the
first half is all about Shandong Theory
and then the second half is how to put
that into action in your daily
meditations so it's kind of a neat uh I
mean the the concept of the book I find
very refreshing you know the first half
is uh all this philosophy and debating
and argument and then the second half is
okay suppose you actually want to get
this view in your own mind you know well
here's some practical meditations you
can do based on scriptures you know so
he made little uh meditations where you
would uh recite something from his
favorite book which what from India
which might be
what sorry
okay he's got all these sections from
the entire temp you can't see the Buddha
you can't hear the DH you can't bow down
to the sun now meditate on that you know
so he would take maybe out of context I
don't know but he would take pieces out
of tant and say okay that meditate on
that for half now and then so it's kind
of a neat book where the first half is
like debates about philosophy and then
the second half is is like practical
meditations to do about
and mixed in there is some Cham like
what to do after your meditation until
your next meditation you know as you're
walking around so personally I find that
a really beautiful method of presenting
atti and I haven't seen it much like
that it's kind of nice you know like
there's a whole long section on how to
meditate on this thing you see I mean
okay J in his book first he goes to the
history of shent and he says it traces
its roots back to Guess Who what well
that for
sure my and my trans five books and
especially
Myra okay and then he says look there
were two great uh translators which are
called sua and um s and
uh I like the way they interpreted T
Tantra if you read the catalog the K and
Tangier and other cataloges these two
translators were working on which
text okay like this was their specialty
also they were working on uh and their
lineage were working
on kakra Tantra which has a lot of
connection with the inner body and the
environment as we spoke about at the
tiger wrer there's a big uh presentation
there about how your environment is a
reflection of your own channels so it's
natural that these llamas would be
interested in the K chakra and
interested in the
Tantra so then he traces it up to Tibet
and then he says look there were three
great llamas who really are are the
fathers of the shentong tradition I
wanted you at least to know their names
I'm not going to do them in tibetan I'm
just going to write them in English Okay
so you don't have to do it in tibetan on
your um on your
homework the first one we already had
actually right he's considered the
forefather of all fall from
ready okay those dat and you already
know about him then the
say
um there something you have to know
about him he was a few
uh well I'll tell you about that later
anyway uh later on this school gets
another name okay the people who were in
love with shent idea God called Jonas
okay
jbas and often times in galupa
scriptures especially in jeta you'll see
oh the Jon says that but uh you know uh
and then he'll he'll argue with him uh
so the jonang ban right is whenever you
see the jonang ban like the big jonang
ban it means one guy out of a school
that went on for 800 years right it's
number two here right okay whenever you
see the J
whenever you say Allon says that but who
who could believe that okay uh this by
jet Jets is referring
to and we'll talk a little bit more
about about the
idea um then uh he's interesting because
he was originally a Saka master and then
he got converted to J he he got
converted to shent he believed it and he
went for it uh then there's a long chain
ra Jamba who was a great nimma
master and got converted to Shen okay so
he's one of the most famous nma Scholars
like you'll often see
longterm famous book by the long he's
also named you'll see him in the reading
as Jim which is one of his other
names and this is his
days so that's the these are the the
important uh fathers of the shenton
tradition listed by
K I'd like to talk a little bit about I
just watching ear history you know
people you should know I mean every
teacher you ever meet in the west will
be from one of these traditions and and
you should be able to know the
differences you know PA M got mad at um
his disciples one day he said what's the
difference between nimma and galupa you
know and they said uh nimma wear a red
hat gupa wear a yellow hat he like you
know like nothing on the ideas that are
different just
the the hat right okay and I'm afraid
that a lot of people are like that okay
I'm afraid that a lot of us are like
that I'm not saying right or wrong bad
or good we're going to talk about that
at the end okay but you should know the
differences clearly you know uh you
should know what you're talking about
like you get in a room with some C
students and you start talking about
common and emptiness they're going to
get confused you're say I never heard
about that you know and then they're
going to start talking about shentong
and you're going to say I never heard of
that you know you should know the
differences and you should be able to
argue the differences that's a basic
thing why do these differences exist
because people think of these things so
it's good to know all the ideas that
people have thought about because it
might pop up in your head a year from
now and there might not be anybody to
ask so it's good to anticipate problems
that your own students might have the
ideas about emptiness that might pop up
in your own students Minds I mean sort
of in America luckily we've gotten
Beyond dark uh the black abyss idea of
emptiness or that it means nothing at
all or something like that uh but then
we got to overcome other ideas like oh
just think about nothing and you'll get
to emptiness or something like that you
know you don't have to study you don't
have to analyze you don't have to think
just close your eyes and float you know
and and this will come to you you know
don't think about anything you know and
and we have to be able to talk about
those like
this so I'm going to talk a little bit
about the tradition called
J uh through which the shentong lineage
passed then we'll get to the
ideas I've never been to Tibet CU I
don't want to go till a three but um say
it's like that you know something like
that and you know here's Nepal ban I
don't know India's down
here and uh H is around here and then
right here there's a town called shate
Chik which is a famous
uh uh town to stop in on the way to
hassa from India you know it's like the
biggest city between H and India it's
the only city I mean and it's where the
British attacked for example in the
early 1900s which is probably why the
Communist end up attacking Tibet that's
thing and um and right around here is a
place called
J there's a a p called J and a monastery
was built
there so they shortened it to Jang
Monastery
J which means Jang
um that was built well let me tell you
first
um the lineage goes like this first is
uh J is the is the county it's like CO's
County and then if the MOG drops out
when you make an adjective so if you
want to say Co C
Virginia uh you just make
it so it means originally it meant
somebody from Jon somebody from the
valley or from the area of Jon the
county of
Jon
of um this lineage begins the janga
minage in some text okay I mean the main
text that I've read it says that yumo
say
yoik d was the one who really started
the Jas they don't know his birth date
or his passing date he lived to 82 or
something like that uh but he lived in
the the 10 hundreds okay 11th
century he wrote some books about
shentong and pretty much got shentong
started it sort of spread slowly and
then a couple of generations later comes
along say
Kang K means gave up everything
sometimes they call it for sometimes
yogis are called that Hermits people go
out and live in the wild place with no
money and stuff like that called C uh TJ
Cinder is his name and he live he's the
one who actually built jonang Monastery
okay so he's like the second big guy in
the Jon
tradition he he said this is worth
building a monastery over probably they
have three guys four guys now you later
it was a big Monastery but at the
beginning it's just usually
a a 30 by3 building or something
whatever all right he built the first
Monastery called uh Jon then you have
uh
say we just had him in the last list
okay 1292 1361
okay the Jang okay he got so famous like
he was so persuasive he was such a good
debator and he presented the shentong
system so well that it's practically
named after I mean he's given the name
of Jang B so when you read Jang the Jang
you're talking about him
D okay so those were the that's sort of
the historical development of this
particular Monastery where shentong
thrived and where shentong started to
spread okay from there then it went goes
into sort of a decline uh after the
1300s it goes into a decline
um
until tarata okay tanata is very famous
tanata he's okay but he has an Indian
name okay like Taran means Dr protect
power
protector and
um he's very well known for his history
of Buddhism your first Reading had some
excerpts from him which Al had to type
in okay and um he's also very famous
because he went to Mongolia and taught
Buddhism there like he was one of the
big figures in Mongolian history so um
when you talk about uh Buddhism in
Mongolia and about their view of
emptiness you get a big jangan push in
Mongolian's view of emptiness
okay uh there's a modern
llama say Jets and D jet I told you a
story the phone call I got right the guy
says I'm the D Lama to that I'm Mongolia
and I'm like sure no I'm like oh I never
heard of you you know he said I'm Jets
Duma you know and I said well uh where's
your Monastery un he said I've never
been to Mongolia and I'm like uh
okay uh well what mon are you from he
says well I never became a monom and I'm
like and you're the D he say yeah I said
well you know he he wanted to meet me in
New York and somebody wanted him to meet
me and I'm like well you know I'm kind
of busy you know maybe we can meet some
other time you know and I hung up and I
went home and told R about it and
laughed about it he says oh you made a
big mistake he is just you know he is
the and he was living
in he was living Liv in a small village
in Southern India his whole life after
the fall of the vent and his Hess
recognized him but kept it secret and
kept him secret because they feared for
his life uh because Mongolia became
communist and if he had returned there
would have been a big uh problem so and
he had uh children I mean he had a wife
and children he never became a mug and
his kids were in K compon in my house
and we used to debate together and one
of them was the monastery truck driver
and one of them was the first diamond
Factory
manager uh but he's considered The
Reincarnation of
Jet and when we got to Mongolia we saw
this huge Palace near the highway and I
said who's who's is that you know and
they said that's Justin D's house you
know I'm like oh Bo and he had never
lived there he had never been there and
then recently he was able to go back and
spent some time there now he's
considered the the main llama in
Mongolia
but I just thought you'd like to see how
t comes up this is considered a galupa
reincarnation so it sort of shifts into
a galupa
reincarnation so now that you know what
janga means okay it's a place Monastery
got named after it famous guy from that
Monastery got called J and then it's and
then it kind of died out and then kind
of revived when I mention a Revival 1700
I meant a Revival in 1575 okay I made a
mistake at the beginning uh I couldn't
remember not days uh but he he
spearheaded The Big Revival in the 1600s
early
1600s I'd like to talk about shenton and
what it means okay and here we get to
the nitty-gritty I mean we're finished
with the background
stuff um I was very anxious to get this
book from jeam Smith because I thought
I'd dive in and find an explanation of
why shenton's called shenton because I
know the gupa version but I thought it
would be really interesting to see the
kagu uh REM version and then uh I've
gone through the text pretty carefully I
don't think he ever says why shenton is
called shanto okay so I sort of
disappointed but then I found another uh
very definitive reference and then
crosschecking um I think it's the best
one I've seen I think it's a really good
one um which is to
say there's
three you got to know something about
the shenton people they consider I mean
some of them
consider I think you could say consider
that the three turnings of the wheel are
not the way you always learned it from
Winston as far as to figurative and
literal they think it's different okay
they have a different tank on it okay
very interesting and this is a big
debate with jet
CA first turning of the wheel we all
agree
was figurative or L figurative by
anybody's standards okay Lord buha
didn't talk much about emptiness didn't
second turning the wheel Lord Buddha
said nothing has any nature of its
own liter according to ma right but the
Jas would say mixed literal and
figurative and then they get to the
third turning of the wheel they they
definitely little because they're very
big into myom okay and you can see how
they're sort of coming out of the minor
scope they are really fixated
on you know they really believe in EN T
okay they really believe in the five
books of my trail as being a message
that the world is my only okay but they
don't call themselves my only okay they
believe in the mind only school but they
don't call themselves M only they
believe in maim if you ask a sh person
are you m only or ma they say we're maim
with the great MAA and they distinguish
between the plain old majima and the
great Ma we the great mumik okay even
those old mikas back in India are just
regular
mumas we're the great Myans okay and
they do draw their system from Indian
sources I mean they say we believe in
the utar Tantra especially and we
believe that my Trias uh brought it to
Tibetans who is M Tria do you
know he was uh one of the other um guys
hanging out in the well guess who was
there naropa I mean I believe MAA was
even one of the guards of the gates as
naropa was but anyway they were hanging
out together in in M Monastery after
naropa went away as a
yogi resigned from the absy it was taken
over later by his student guess
who he was sort of a
stickler so yeah he's a little more
concered Lord AA okay so you got Lord AA
and my Tria in the same monastery now
Chip is this great ttic Yogi who really
liked to do a wild
situ and uh we have records that he was
actually disciplined by Lord AA for his
uh wild SES you know and he kind of said
you know then one of Martha's teachers
whenever Mara wasn't around Thea he
would go hang out with ma Chupa and Ma
Chupa also taught him T so so anyway if
you ask a shentong or Jona what are they
who's the big Indian scholar that you
follow say oh we're straight M Tria
Mya's version of the Tantra is what
we're selling you know Andra
is but the way they presented is pure
mind only okay so that's you start to
get a feel so what is the basic uh what
are the most Winston the N somebody
else what are the most important two
ideas of the minor
School say
again
sh those of you stud I mean a man
right here's us here's
them what's mean
uh the conscious
constructs constructs imaginary things
things that in your mind okay you can
say
construct mental
construct like uh there could be a
person who irritates me that wasn't
coming from
my is a construct the person who
irritates you who wasn't created by
you okay the person who shocks you or
bothers you who didn't come from
you okay is a construct two kinds of
constructs what
some do exist and some don't exist I
mean that one doesn't happen to exist
okay that's just a plain old mental
fabrication you can think of this as a
mental fabrication okay no such thing ex
this uh
Shen so happens to mean like nominal
construct fabrication of the Mind how
about shenon anybody
huh other yeah sh means other one means
power means under the power of other
things you can call dependent things or
changing things anything that's caused
by another thing and therefore and
therefore depends on another thing for
its
existence in the way that a tree depends
on its seed okay so we can call it
depending things
or you can call it we're going to call
it cause things through are
changing you don't want to call it other
power uh I don't know it gets a little
weird people forget what it
means but you can when you teach it you
can call it that and then explain it you
know depends on it depends on how much
of a lingo you want to
invent yeah and I just want to say
that the more you you go into another
lingo to present ideas the more people
you
lose when Buddhism becomes a a lingo
that you have to learn that the the
English is V SAA takes his damaru and
goes with his do to talk to you know and
then you already got three words and no
you don't have a word yet that an
English speaker would know and then
they're just like you know you got to
remember that words that are familiar to
you after 5 years or 10 years of study
your students aren't going to know
necessarily so you want to back up into
normal English as far as you can okay
okay so depending things cause or
changing things y do
anybody emptiness it means totality
right because
what say
again it's all related all pervasive all
pervasive good yeah yeah it covers
everything emptiness is called totality
in the mind only school because it
covers the totality of all things it
spreads to All Things everything's got
its own
emptiness everything's got its own
how many of these things
are deceptive reality and how many are
Ultimate
Reality according to
us yeah these two are normal reality
let's got normal or deceptive reality
this all has a point don't
worry and this
one this one is
ultimately now I get to them now we get
to
them according to and everybody else is
the
wisdom
okay get used to it get used to it we're
wearing shentong hat tonight you got to
Def defend it you know like it's your
life you know what's
y wisdom of non duality nality of what
subject and object what do you mean
they're nality they're the same thing
there's no separate subjects not
to
okay and the wisdom that perceives that
perceives clear light and that wisd
wisdom is clear
light wisdom mixed with clear light is
uh
[Music]
young wouldn't they figure out that they
were
mistaken we'll get into that we'll get
okay got it I mean this is the the big
uh crack in the head right I mean this
is Winston's
car okay all right okay so this is
Ultimate Reality and it is devoid of
deceptive
Shen these two things are
Shen sorry that's
sh normal reality which deceives you
okay everything in this room that you
can see in a normal day on a normal day
if you inv like me
okay is the other in emptiness of other
and this wisdom mixed somehow with
emptiness or which they would call Nal
clear light sorry this wisdom mixed with
their emptiness that they call light is
other sh than these two things so it's
empty of of normal stuff okay it's empty
of normal stuff
and that's the real meaning of shent
okay that's the real meaning of shent to
put it very
basically wisdom or emptiness in our
terms or wisdom plus emptiness somehow
is defined
as that which is empty of all the other
stuff that which is the void of all
normal stuff is Ultimate wisdom plus and
now here's the punch sign you ready
what's this got to do with our
course what are we studying this course
where are we at right now in the seven
Diamond like
Visions r at come red Buddha nature
what's this whole presentation got to do
today with B GUI Michael why did you
bring this is all very interesting we
always want to know the history of the
of the I can't remember what Jas but uh
what's that got to do with our class you
know why' you bring that up at this
point because G of J brought it up at
this point because G of J brings it up
at this point because according to the
Jas this is guess what good
nature okay this is PR
nature come on you guys I mean and and
by the way well let me read it to you
directly
I'm not making fun big mistake big
mistake this is very serious hundreds of
thousands of people believed in this 800
years
okay um so the homework question said
like how does the idea of other
emptiness or shentong relate to the
Buddha nature which is the subject of
our class okay here's the answer as
noted above other emptiness refers to
the wisdom or state of mind or wisdom
oops which perceives that subjects and
objects are not separate non-duality
right somehow mixed with emptiness right
here's how his hus Karma the third
karmapa describes it in according to
jamun okay this is
jamun uh
paraphrasing um the third K in his book
he says that primordial mind the state
of indivisible ether and wisdom ether
meaning like emptiness okay which is
like a reflection of the Moon in water
I'll say it again okay beyond all true
or false that which cannot ever be
identified and beyond all
names okay that's how that's how the the
beginner of the shentong system
describes uh Buddha nature okay you
ready I'll say it again uh the proning
of mind and you can read it in the
reading this is uh what Winston's been
working on the state of indivisible
ether and wisdom which is like a
reflection of the Moon and water beyond
all true or false that which cannot be
ever be identified and beyond all names
and later he gets like more poetic I
mean k says not big not small not here
not there uh can't be seen can't be
descried there is a unit what with a
go what is that song C
no no it was
Alison she was driving through Texas she
heard this R song on the radio she gets
it for us and ret treat we get this tape
right there is
a university
CC anyway it's some guy from Texas
there's universe that can't be seen
can't be explained can't
be beyond all s you know it's like be
okay
anyway uh so you immediately see one
problem that the
any school of India would have with this
with this idea which is what it's
contained
here they say that this thing has been
in beings since beginning this
time okay this pury has been in beings
since beginning this time this wisdom
has no mental afflictions it is pure
uh and it's been in you since
beginningless
time and it is emptiness also it is the
clear light meaning emptiness supp to
changing and unchanging beautiful
beautiful okay so Ted says so it's
supposed to changing and unchanging
thing why what's the changing thing
what's the unchanging thing the changing
thing would be would be the mind the WID
yeah unchanging the EMP the unchanging
thing is the emptiness so it's already a
contradiction of terms it's like saying
it's like very weird it's like to say it
in tobet is toing Li toing lle means
unchanging functioning thing a thing
that could do its thing a thing which
could affect other objects a pen which
could ride a car which could drive um
food which could feed you without
changing because by doing something to
somebody you what you change energy is
transferred okay whenever you do
something you
change so the idea here is of a an
unchanging functional thing a thing that
works but never changes okay and that's
like a big no no in what
course 13 come on I mean big no no since
ancient India you know a functioning
thing that that never changes what's the
other example we had in Shanti DEA for
that functioning thing that made a lot
of stuff but didn't
change God God
God we have a problem with that we have
a problem with that never changes made
everything okay I mean that's just the
same idea it's the same so anyway that's
that's one of the first um problems that
we have with
SH
uh I wanted to rub that
in by uh quoting jba who's jba
yeah sh johs
right here's his version of
uh of what it is to be shenton or Buddha
nature right they're now
what they're not like synonyms they're
now like synonyms okay that's why sh
relates to Buddha
nature Buddha heart right Buddha Essence
um here's how Jona himself describes the
two kinds of Buddha nature ready what
are the two kinds of budha nature
yeah Ric which is like your natural
Buddha nature that you were born with
and it's always been there any other
one stuff that can turn into Buddha
right developable stuff but here's his
definition getting the natural or inate
or innate Buddha nature is an actual
Buddha complete with the 32 qualities of
Enlightenment okay like 32 marks of
Enlightenment or you can say the 32 High
spiritual qualities and Enlightenment
there's 64 total
actually which has existed for all
time as a component
part of every suffering living
being s right I'll say it again innate
Buddha nature is an actual
Buddha complete with all the qualities
of
enlightenment which has existed for all
time as a component part of every
suffering living being you have a little
buddha inside of 100% Buddha already
Buddha okay and you've had it for all
time developable Buddha nature then
consists
of new occasions of Buddha
nature which are created as one engages
in learning and other AC activities like
that
okay so developable Buddha nature
consists of occasions new occasions of
Buddha nature which are
Crea like you can think of them as new
seeds that are put in your mind from my
talk tonight okay I mean that's not such
a weird idea right I'm talking tonight
you're getting certain ideas they are
certain seeds in your mind they're going
to help you grow into a Buddha okay
they're going to develop into a Buddha
that one's that one's not so crazy right
okay the other one is the is the idea
that you already have part and parcel
with you fully enlightened Buddha so you
know G of J is like I'm going to give
you g of J at the end but I think I'll
throw him in as the things go on Okay g
g of J says look so that means it's uh
bakaya right I mean the big one
dharmakaya right the body of essence the
Essence body of the Buddha right he is
in you already right yeah so it's got
the two kinds of Purity right
yeah what are the two kinds of Purity a
empty from the beginning B free of all
mental afflictions Etc from the
beginning okay so if you already have a
fully developed Buddha inside you then
your mind is already free in the two
ways already D sure in the two ways what
are the two ways one empty two no mental
afflictions come on why'd you write your
book okay I mean that that gu was
hot not
easy you know and then you can debate
you know if this were a real diamond
mountain September 2004 you'd have an
assignment to go home to the to the
debate ground and and you know let them
defend themselves a little bit you know
don't leave it there and what would he
say he' say it's there but it's
covered this just
cover doesn't that you become exist all
times
yeah you you got to say that for the
debate we won't
get uh you go over the definition
of consists of of nature which arise as
you as you hear a class Etc to you see
and that's not such a strange idea right
I mean you're getting seeds planted
tonight that will contribute to your
Enlightenment I hope okay and that's
developable you see that's going to
develop and get better and better and
then it's going to help you become
that's okay that's the first one that we
have a problem with there's a Buddha
already inside
of with complete with the two kinds of
Purity meaning complete with no mental
funs the mind has no mental fictions
that then were like just to let you know
I mean g j is really getting upset uh do
you know why Buddha nature comes up at
this point in the text of the utra me we
didn't cover that you'll see it in the
reading
they say j j says how how do we get to
come you know how do we get to
uh to Buddha nature in a discussion of
it happens to be a discussion of the
qualities of a Buddha you see of the
things you have to learn to become a
Buddha he says well the idea is that all
this stuff that you learn purifies your
Buddha nature you know your Buddha
nature is all mixed up right we
said you're you have an emptiness of
your mind but it's Stained It's tainted
and you have have to go about purifying
it right you have to go about purifying
it
so you know there's a debate in the
entire temp why does calm come up here
why are you talking about goodd nature
here because we're talking about
purification what's that have to do with
C what do you think you're purifying
you're purifying your Cal you're
purifying your Buddha nature your Buddha
nature is
stained uh your budha nature is Tainted
by these other things so if you start
talking about purifying of course you're
already talking about Buddha nature come
so that's how the whole argument starts
right so now you're going to have to get
into well do you have anything so so let
me get this straight I called we talked
about it Christy and IAL we were trying
to thres this out right we decided that
uh Rick for uh this guy is a crystal
golf ball Crystal golf ball and it's got
like mud around it you know so he what
he's trying to what he's saying is that
look the crystal call is pure but it's
like covered with mud now where that M
where would that idea come from number n
number nine that's not so weird time
said down Buddha image B with jewels and
covered with mud and then if you could
just get the mud off you could find the
the true Buddha inside you right that's
where this is all coming from so you can
feel how it's coming true true
nature can't ask me if I
uh but I give you this thought and may
not let you have a break okay I'm sorry
cuz I'm really into this I give you this
thought I give you this thought see how
easy it is to slip from an image into a
wrong idea of
emptiness you know see how you when you
want to describe emptiness to somebody
you might say diamond right it was like
a diamond and then they start getting
this picture of a diamond and then after
a few centuries it's emptiness is a
diamond big diamond mountain diamond B
Diamond everything you know must you
must be I think he was saying it was
like a a gem you know a clear gem a
solid thing you know because the mind
can't hold on to the idea of Buddha
nature being the simple absence of
something you see it's so hard for the
mind it's so hard for the human mind and
95% of people who ever hear about
emptiness are still holding on to some
kind of black or some kind of diamond or
some kind of clear light you see instead
of instead of um whatever I got in my
hand no and it's that simple absence you
know it's that simple absence the simple
killing get up gone you know it's not
there that's all but how do you
communicate that to somebody you see
without them making an image out of it
you know like that's the big thing in in
Islam right don't make an image out of
me I'm not like that you know and uh
don't not make to yourself any graven
images I'm not like that I'm a daki I'm
just you know and then but you attach to
images you know the colonel and the seed
the the the world emperor in the womb
the you know and then you get schools
going on for a thousand years of people
thinking that that Buddha nature is a SE
in the sense of a
a positive thing because it's so hard to
hold on
to the greatest call you have is the
fact that you ain't got something that
you never could have had anyway that you
think you had okay now hold on to that
try to teach that for hundreds of years
and it just doesn't go we need a
something solid you know and I think
that's very you know just a tiny slip in
your worldview you're here just a tiny
slip it's not like something crazy it's
like a tiny slip you start thinking of
good nature as a seed rather than an
absence I've even used the word seed
over and over in these classes just to
try to communicate you know and then and
then it gets spread that way okay I
think we'll stop there did you have a
question if it's an absence how do you
how do you what needs to
be nothing it's unchanging
thing your cover that ah then you start
sounding like know yeah you do
you debate
it ready no it's a good
point do do we would we say that things
obscured are attached to the nature that
obscure
it or is it your own perceptions that
obscure it is
mean I think that's what but if we would
say that Buddha nature is something that
needs to be purified in order to become
a Buddha then it
yeah but what does chefi mean can can
100% emptiness can the 100% absence of
something be made any more
absolute you see so that can't be what
purification means right you see so it
has to mean something else to us or
we're thinking of good in nature as some
sort of positive thing
yeah okay take a I'm
sorry
uh your number school I just want to go
on to one more thing the januma school
it's kind of shocking to me when I read
it but they say um we're the great
mikas and then those other maikas back
in India were the regular
maikas and um I wanted to explain to you
why you know they go into an explanation
of why all right
uh and GS of J picks on them for calling
themselves great maikas later as you
might guess so uh here we
go
um those regular followers of M M are
always saying that all existing objects
are empty of any essence of their
own okay those regular mind guys are
always saying that all object objects
are emptiness of any essence of their
own which is what the mum schools do
say what's the big version of emptiness
for the M only by the way
remember what is that subject and object
yeah subject and object are are
empty coming from a separate seed okay
which everybody can relate to you know
one seed has created me to stand here
one seed has created Michael for me to
see okay so in a sense We Are One
Essence one
substance which is not at all to say I'm
Michael and Michael M or there's no
difference between us okay when we say
object and subject are not different we
mean not different see you know but we
are different in in the normal ways in
the imputed ways okay um but if you
didn't understand the mind only School
you might think that that was the main
idea of emptiness that me and Michael
there's no Duality between subject and
object somehow I am Michael Michael is
me and the illusion is that he seems to
be separate from mus well they would say
separate you see separate seed I don't
have a problem with separate from me I
have a problem you see they slipped they
slipped you see and that you know you
hear that so often it's so indefensible
and you don't go anywhere with that okay
so I'm Michael where do I go now you
know what I how do I practice that you
know like uh so I'm the wall you know
there's no difference between me and the
wall so where do you go with that you
know how do you develop yourself how do
you
practice Buddhism with that and then
people get frustrated and just kind of
leave it you know and then they're
looking for something else you know
they're looking for something that has
an application in your life you know
yeah the Wall's not as as separate as I
thought it used to be the wall is a
projection of my past Karma if I wanted
a nicer wall I could maybe provide
housing for other people who come to D
and know you know that's has
applications you see that could lead to
a Buddha Paradise okay
anyway all those regular M guys they say
all existing things are empty of any
essence of the real and the lower
schools think's talking about the first
two schools Abid and logic
okay they talk about the lack of self to
a person
right and they say there's a lack of
Truth to objects okay Lack of self to a
person lack of Truth to object objects
they talk about that individually but
they never get up to where we are
okay and those yoga systems they speak
about the wisdom that's beyond the own
okay they talk
about
but because all these views are still
mistaken I'm quoting uh sh I'm quoting J
text okay they are far from
Enlightenment like they got a long way
to
go the only people who can really have
any experience of the wisdom free of
Duality are either people who are
perceiving it
directly or those whose minds are
trained to meditating on nothing at
all or on empty
space those the forget the forget the ab
Dharma School forget the Sutra School
forget the mind only School forget the
old manum school you got to get up to
the the great maans why because only
we have the real experience of non how
we put our minds into a state of
nothing for getet this study forget this
ananalysis forget this like you know
they say stop grinding your nose stop
putting your nose to the grinding room
they say that just cool it just take it
easy close your eyes meditate on there's
no big or small there's no Sam Nirvana
there's no antidote there's no
problem just put your mind into empty
space we're the only ones who understand
that so we're the great
mind
okay the idea that analysis or
contemplation and anness could be useful
is a
delusion that's a quotation
now if you're in a debate ground and you
were playing the Jona you'd probably
want to respond to that you know I
didn't you know all I meant and he says
it later on he says another thing he
says
look there's this guy they never mention
him
okay uh just a coup he keeps talking
about analizing stuff thinking hard
about stuff ripping stuff
[Music]
apart you know if you try to find this
object that doesn't exist you know you
never find it you know it's too much
sweat too much logic too much thinking
you know just get down and get into
non-discursive thought you know that
stuff is not
meditation you know that's not
meditation and there's
scriptural uh foundation for that we had
it in the yoga do
you
meaning yeah these four kinds of uh
meditation just get you to the former
you know trying to calm your mind down
trying to feel better trying
to Anda you know kind of looking at the
object deeply looking at the object not
so deeply but there's still no emptiness
content to that you're still in
discursive mental thought process no
matter how far you go without bringing
up emptiness you still going to get
caught in Samar you're just feeling
better you know you feel better but
you're you're not getting out of samsar
you don't have that emptiness element
you see which everyone agrees is
necessary to get out some so it's not
like a crazy accusation you know like
they are taking this from the ancient
scriptures you know just put your mind
on nothing just don't think about
anything you know empty space and you
see that even like uh
Western uh authors of your lineages you
you see that even in um modern books you
see calm down don't be so tense you know
just relax sit at quietly go on your
breath and then just empty space you
know and when you get a problem with
somebody or something comes up just let
go you know and it's a very common uh
that's where it's all coming from it's
all from uh old
J yeah is isn't that the same argument
with kamila in the
Chinese young years earlier
yeah right yeah it is it is the fact
that they had the debate and the fact
thatan almost
won it tells you that you know it's it's
a common and it's not it's not crazy you
know there is a place where you have to
take reasoning and then get to the
object and then there's a difference
between Cho and Joo right analyze
analyze analyze conclusion emptiness Jo
fix on it you know what I mean there is
a place for that um but they were very
frustrated with jeta what's this Chum
stuff right I listen analytical
meditation what are you talking about
meditation is a time for sitting and not
thinking about
anything and and that was their that's
what distinguishes great mind maker from
the others they got all these theories
all this
ideas and they debate them and they
think about them and rip them apart but
we we sit down you think about in this
space that's
it anybody else is far from buddh this
is
a quotation
okay
and we're just about done I wanted to
State uh formally G J's for G of J's
complaints okay about shenton when he
gets to Shen when he gets to the end of
shentong he says um you know I'm sorry
to to go so long on this shentong idea
but but so many people are thinking
about it nowadays that I felt obliged
you know when you read um k j kol
defense of shentong he says so many
people are attacking shentong nowadays I
thought I should stop for a moment and
just clarify it you know so it's kind of
cool you get both sides of the both of
them are apologizing for going on but
they feel like it's necessary okay so
we're going to give um G four of G
complaints the wisdom which procees that
there's well I'm just going to say non
du wisdom right wisdom that sees that me
and Michael are not
separate is budage is is unchanging
budage that's the G J's first complaint
we already talked about right we already
talked about that
the second is we also went over already
if my mind is already the Buddha from
the
beginning then it must possess the two
kinds of
Purity one it's pure of self-existent
things from the beginning we all agreed
to that two is it is it pure of all bad
thoughts negative thoughts they have to
say what
yesd that's the definition of
the the body which has the two purities
so then they're forced into saying my
mind from beginning of this time has not
had mental
afflictions so we're already
[Music]
Buddhist Here Comes an interesting one
what's the Shen and
shent but what is
sh Shen and everything in the
room whether they exist or not you know
like ideas that you have Concepts that
you have and also all the stuff that you
can see here and Buddha nature or
shenton is that which is other than
those things that which is empty of
those other things Shen okay good in
nature is the state of mind which
perceives nality and is other than those
things it doesn't possess those things
anymore so God say so let me get this
straight you're saying that this wisdom
which procees
nity
uh is free of normal stuff and they say
that's what
yeah yeah Ultimate
Reality is the absence of deceptive
reality so he says now let me get this
straight do you mean yaa or yima okay
inet Mak a big difference are you saying
it's not involved with deceptive reality
or you saying it isn't deceptive reality
something other than deceptive reality
is that with the shin is that what
you're trying to get at so it gives them
two choices right it's a diamond deal
two bad choices right I'll say it again
are you saying that uh like your version
of Ultimate Reality like is just not
involved with normal
stuff right
like are you saying it's not normal
stuff like which which one are you
talking about it has to be one of the
two and if they say oh Ultimate Reality
means Shen means empty of other meaning
it's just not involved at all with
normal stuff anymore it's
beyond so he says okay so uh it's not
buha nature anymore right why' you say
that of course it's budha nature oh so
does it spread to every living cre
does every living creature have it
within them as part of their being from
beginning this
time well yeah well are they deceptive
reality or Ultimate Reality what they're
deceptive reality so is it like in
intimately linked with deceptive reality
things since beginning this time what do
you mean it's empty of other things what
do you mean shend okay so that's his
first problem you got it you okay on
that
one okay what do you mean you mean
Ultimate Reality is got is empty of
normal reality in the sense that they're
not related at all and he says right
that's what I mean come on you're saying
that this is Buddha nature you're saying
Buddha nature spreads to every suffering
living creature since beginning this
time what do you think they are they're
they're normal reality it's it what do
you call it impregnates it uh how' you
say it pervades every single existing
being you can't say it's not connected
to anything you can't say it's empty of
other right empty of of normal things he
say okay I take I'm sorry let's take it
back let's go the other
way uh it's empty of being Ultimate
Reality is empty of being normal reality
okay that's what Shandong
means then G of J says did you have to
write all these books just for
that you know I
mean you say that you are great maans
right so you say that you're your
disciples have somehow perceived
something that other people couldn't
perceive like they
are
W they are spiritually Advanced
intellectual disciples you know so do
you have to go through this whole thing
to tell them Ultimate Reality is not
normal reality I mean if it just means
empty of normal reality did you have to
go through writing all these books just
so they' know that of course it's empty
of normal reality of course it's
different from nor CH I I can buy that
ultimate reality is different from
normal reality so then why do you call
yourself big monum makers why do you say
that everybody else didn't get it right
and you and your disciples get it right
you know what who that's a no-brainer
he's just saying come on that's a no
brain of course of course Ultimate
Reality is empty of normal
reality
okay uh last
one you say that thinking and Analysis
are of no benefit in reaching the wisdom
which is free of all Duality which can
only be reached through thoughtless
meditation why then do you undertake for
example to explain your shentong to
people if analysis and contemplation of
emptiness is of no value and if
emptiness can only be approached in a
Mindless state of deep
meditation why' you write your
book why do youy why are you trying to
explain it to us
all
right
uh by the way these are you know to be
really fair you got to have a sheno
person here to defend themselves I'm
sure they'd have answers right and then
you'd have to go deeper it's kind of
mean to pick on somebody who's not there
um I threw in two more points in the
reading because I thought they're really
beautiful you know we've been picking
on shenton tonight but um there's a
beautiful part at the end of
jamol's text that I thought it would be
beautiful to include in the reading and
you know Jung was no dummy he was
extremely talented brilliant writer
probably a Buddha okay llama and he
says these are his final advice for
practice like on the last few pages of
the Practical part of the book he says
look feel deep love and belief that the
Lama who Parts these essential
instructions to you is the dharmakaya
itself like just believe the last thing
after all this debate philosophy stuff
like that you get up out of your morning
meditation you go meet your llama you
say I meet the dharm this is the
D this is emptiness of
the right there you know with great love
and I'm in the presence of the
that's technically illegal and
Practically Perfect okay right I'm in
the presence of the
D and then I love the next one he says
reflect to yourself that since all
living beings possess the bo of
nature then whether you are able at this
point to recognize it or not they all
ultimately combine within themselves all
the qualities of an enlightened being it
just means come on the purpose of
talking about Buddha nature practically
speaking whatever you call it doesn't
matter when you meet other people just
concentrate on that this is an
enlightened being about to
happen this is an enlightened being
about to go on especially if they're
sitting in a class like this you know
like when you get into a group like this
and you're sitting with a bunch of
people like this just appreciate where
you're all at you know look at them and
say my God you know we got 20 30 people
here about to break into enlightenment
you know on the cusp you know and and
enjoy you know enjoy it walk around
saying godamn it you know those people
on Tucson city street they got put
in you know everybody walking around the
streets got in I'm lucky we're lucky you
know this is unbelievable you know and
you got to think like that then he calls
it
do means uh like that bu about 140
uh see everything as pure you know just
stop worrying about little differences
between us you know come on everybody
walking around has got Buddha nature the
Iraqis have Buddha nature you know the
terrorists have Buddha nature you know
uh the
Jers you know like we all got B AG so
just be happy and enjoy you know it's
amazing you know and he's like come on
you know don't stick your head up your
butt sometimes I think a lot of
Buddhists have their head up there you
know and uh it's like come on look where
we're at everybody in this new's got
good nature we're just about to become L
you know so have a good time
okay
uh you know somebody asked me this oh
when would you figure out that this view
was wrong if you held it
right and uh you know the body BS the
first one especially uh Dr Shim she know
you know you can't criticize especially
other schools of
Buddism and
um if anybody is a de on this planet I'm
sure K was a de you see I mean J I mean
what are the odds someone who writes all
this stuff goes so deep affects so many
hundreds of thousands of people and he's
not a Buddha or he's not somebody
special you know so the question comes
up in the monastery you know why do
people like M tra present my only school
you know it's mistaken it's slightly
wrong you know why do you get my M tra
teaching these wrong ideas you know even
about Buddha nature you know why would
Lord M Traya do that and uh there's a
clue on the first page of
Juno's scripture and I kind of like it
you know there's a there's a clue right
there on the front page you know it's
kind of beautiful he says
um I'm going to quote him okay it's not
that we make this distinction between
literal and figurative teachings because
there's any chance that some part of
Lord beus teachings could be intentional
lies you know it's not like we say this
is literal and this is figurative
because we think Lord Buddha was a liar
or that he's trying to mislead us you
know what what do you think you know
it's just that different people have
different capacities to see what the
deepest teachings you know different
people have different capacities
you know this whole three wheels thing
the three turning of the wheel thing he
says it's just like uh what does he
[Music]
say
say and I didn't know this word and I
looked it up in the dictionary you know
and it says
um when a mother is trying to feed a
piece of fruit for example to a child
and they can't stick it in their mouth
and they can't bite it they have to mash
it
they have to make it all mush like
Gerber's baby frood you know and then
they have to you like spoon it in that's
what Lord spirit is doing come on don't
you get it you know uh you're being
spoonfed the baby gby stuff at first you
know is it's not that Lord Buddha is
trying to lie or mislead you about
Buddha nature when he talks about this
clear light stuff and all that he's just
um mashing it up for you so you can
digest it and then later you can get the
Sol
so the fact that he says that on the
front page and then goes on to like 25
pages of
indefensible emptiness teachs that are
very attractive to many people uh is I
think he's trying to say something you
know that's my take on it
okay what if you spend your whole life
studying this to see this is way things
are etc etc would that preclude you from
the direct perception of emptiness
because you're spending your time
spacing
out I think it it could be very
dangerous yeah it could be very
dangerous but maybe for a
person uh well they say who doesn't have
the you just don't have enough so you
get them to do other things like at the
end he says I don't care what you do you
know look just go make some um water
bowl off you know go build a stoa go do
uh you know something physical you know
and and dedicated to seeing Rick you see
like he has a whole list of activities
and he
says if if you don't if Rick doesn't
come to you easily you have to go do
some other things first and then Rick
will come to you and and he actually
there mentions for the first and only
time G developable
you got to develop it you see so um yeah
I think uh somebody told me somebody at
vajani which is a big galupa Center in
the United States that the former
director said it wasn't him but a good
friend of his uh so I never would have
gotten into Buddhism if Trum hadn't
taken me to all those drinking FS you
know you know and people say bad things
about at least they used to about Trum
you know like 30 years ago it was like a
big Scandal Trum is just alcoholic and
doing we K and but you don't know but he
said you don't know how many people
ended up going there for the party and
then you know 6 months later they're
like studying man so you don't know you
can't
St all
right we'll start we'll
start
[Music]
for fore